Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף כ"א, Daf Kaf Aleph,
we've already begun במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin and we pick up at
the very top of כ"א עמוד א', Kaf Aleph Amud Aleph, the
first line, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. I should mention just in terms
of an issue that came up yesterday where it said that you
cannot use שעוה, sha'ava, wax,
תוספות Tosafot does bring down an opinion basically that you cannot use
wax candles. In the end תוספות Tosafot says though that you can
because the גמרא Gemara says you cannot use wax as a fuel,
as an oil, but you can use it as a wick. And
basically the argument that תוספות Tosafot makes is that if you have
a wax candle basically it's all wick. That basically what your wax
candle is, it's a wick surrounded by wax, just very thick wax.
And basically halakhically that's how we use wax candles and that's how
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules, that the case where the גמרא
Gemara says you cannot use wax is if you have a wick
out of
thread and you have sort of wax below it and the goal
is for the wick to draw up the wax. So that is
where it says wax does not work. But what we do, which
is we wrap the wick with wax, it's all really considered to
just be a very thick wick. So that's how we actually are
allowed to use wax candles, that's based on תוספות Tosafot and that's
how it's ruled in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. Obviously there's
no but that's the point because to say that the גמרא Gemara
is only prohibiting the case or disallowing the case where the wax
is like separated off from the wick. But when it surrounds the
wick obviously the fuel is I understand it's the same thing but
presumably the argument is that the mechanics work differently. I don't know,
I've never tried doing the candle where you have just a wick
on top and the wax collected on the bottom. I assume that
the wax does not draw up a wick as
easily so it has to melt first and that's why a candle
works is because the flame causes the wax immediately around it to
melt. So the mechanics are actually different and that's how we rule,
yes.
And we rule the same way for paraffin, which is what most
candles are made of.
Well very right, but Michael is asking about beeswax and so on,
so even wax which is referred to, that's only when it's separated
from the wick. Okay, so now let's continue at the very top
of כ"א עמוד א'. Kaf Aleph Amud Aleph. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
אלו דברים שאין מדליקין בהן, Elu devarim she'ein madlikin bahen, those things
that they said you cannot use to light בשבת, b'Shabbos, אבל עושין
מהן מדורה, aval osin meihen medurah, but you can use them to
attach it here about the wicks, those things that cannot be used
for wicks, nevertheless if you want to use them as type of
a bonfire,
בין להתחמם כנגדה, bein lehit-hamen kenegdah, and maybe this even includes also
the oils and the various things that can't be used, again that's
only if it's a classic, this sort of picks up on the
theme I just said, if it's a classic type of a lamp
configuration where the goal is to have the oil drawn up by
the wick. Okay and there there are those things that some things
function well as oils and some don't, some function well as wicks
and some don't. But if you want to use these materials to
make a bonfire out of it, בין להתחמם כנגדה, bein lehit-hamen kenegdah,
whether your interest is to use it for heat, because then you
would think if you use it for heat maybe in one scenario
there's more of a concern of fiddling with it than another, בין
להשתמש לאורה, bein lehishtamesh l'orah, whether you want to use it for
light, either way, בין על גבי קרקע בין על גבי כירה bein
al gabei karka bein al gabei kireh or some מנורה, menora, whether
it's on the ground, whether it's on top of your oven or
on top of some type of a lamp, some type of a
base. All these cases is totally fine.
The only those were not a concern, the concern was specifically when
you wanted to use these things in a lamp type of a
configuration. ולא אסרו אלא לעשות מהן פתילה לנר בלבד. V'lo asru ela
la'asot meihen petilah l'ner bilvad. So here we're talking about the problematic
wicks, only to be a wick for a lamp. But to use
in other types of configurations it would be fine, even if you're
using it for light. But it's when it's specifically this mechanics of
a oil being drawn up a wick, there it really matters what
the oil is and what the wick is. Anybody that's ever tried
to use oil מנורות menoros knows it's tricky. So there it really
does matter. Okay. ולא בשמן קיק. V'lo b'shemen kik. And now we
continue about the problematic oils.
ולא בשמן קיק, V'lo b'shemen kik, not with oil of קיק. kik.
מאי שמן קיק? Mai shemen kik? What's oil of קיק? kik? אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שאלתי לכל נחותי ימא, sha'alti l'chol nuchasei yama, once
again I asked all the people that went down to the sea,
the seafarers, the importers, ואמרו לי, v'amru li, עוף אחד יש בכרכי
הים, oph echad yesh b'charkhei hayam, there's a certain bird in the
islands, וקיק שמו, v'kik shemo, and it's called קיק, kik, so this
is oil made out of the fat of that bird or some
type of a way of processing the bird.
רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה אומר, Rav Yitzchak breih d'Rav Yehuda omer,
משחא דקאזא. mishcha d'kaza. No, it's oil of קאזא. kaza. What's קאזא?
kaza? רש"י Rashi says קאזא kaza is cotton. If you look at
רש"י Rashi says גרעיני צמר גפן שקורין כותנא, garinei tzemmer gefen shekorin
kutton, from the seeds of cotton which they call kutton, cotton. It's
the last רש"י Rashi on the wide line. No, it’s oil of
כזא. Kaza. What’s כזא? Kaza? So רשי Rashi says כזא Kaza is
cotton. If you look at רשי Rashi says גרעיני צמר גפן Garinei
Semer Geffen from the seeds of cotton שקורין כותין, Shekorin Kutin, cotton.
The last רשי Rashi on the wide line, cotton oil, correct.
What’s the problem with cotton oil?
Again, the assumption is that all these things do not burn evenly
and they, the flame will flicker and you’ll come to adjust it.
I’ve never tried, I’ll have to try.
Go ahead and try it also. But we also don’t know if
the way we process it is the same way they processed it.
So, but you can go ahead and you can all do experiments
and come back and tell me.
Okay, so next, we’re allowed to use it for at least למדורה,
L’medura, right?
What do you mean?
It says here that we’re allowed to...
when you make a bonfire out of it, not when you make
a, not when you’re using it as a lamp. Okay, all that
stuff before is if you want to make out of it a
bonfire. Okay,
okay. ריש לקיש אמר קיקיון דיונה, Resh Lakish Amar Kikayon d’Yona, the
קיקיון דיונה. Kikayon d’Yona. Now רשי Rashi immediately says not exactly the
same one of יונה, Yona, רשי Rashi says the first narrow line
of רשי, Rashi, כעין אותה של יונה, Ke’ein otah shel Yona, we
mean the one described in ספר יונה, Sefer Yona, that species, not
exactly the one that יונה Yona sat under. So what is the
קיקיון? Kikayon?
So Steinsaltz looks, says that it’s a castor, a castor plant. Although
I don’t know, you know, he didn’t describe, what I was waiting
to hear was what was the קיקיון Kikayon that, you know, that
provided him the shade and so on. He doesn’t, what?
From the picture it’s not a shade tree.
Yeah, I know. The גמרא Gemara in a minute is going to
also mention people that sit under the shade. So he didn’t really
discuss that, but he claims that,
but anyway, but Steinsaltz says that it is a, that that’s a
castor plant. All right, so that’s what he says. Now, it says:
אמר רבה בר בר חנה. Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Chana. So רבה
בר בר חנה Rabbah Bar Bar Chana said: לדידי חזי לי קיקיון
דיונה, L’didi chazi li kikayon d’Yona, I saw the קיקיון דיונה Kikayon
d’Yona and once again רשי Rashi says not the exact same one
of יונה, Yona, okay, but I saw that type of plant. How
do you know?
Yeah,
right. Okay, fine. All right, anyway. ולצליבא דמי, U’l’tsuliva dami, and it
is similar to a צליבא. Tsuliva. What’s a צליבא? Tsuliva? רשי Rashi
says what a צליבא Tsuliva is, רשי Rashi says it’s a certain
type of a, of a tree. I forget what Steinsaltz, gave some
name for it which did not mean anything to me. What? Ricinus?
Ricinus, okay, there you go. It’s a Ricinus tree. Okay, anyway, the
ערוך Aruch says it’s some type of a non-fruit-bearing tree. All right,
so I saw it. Now he’s going to tell you something about
it.
ומדפסקי רביי, U’midpaski rabbei, it grows from the swamps,
ועל פום חנותא מדבניא, V’al pum chanuta madvanya, and they sort of
suspend it, they drape it over the doorways of stores. It’s some
type of an attractive thing that gets customers, makes the store look
nice. ומפרצדוהי עבדי משחא, U’mi’partzadohi avdi mishcha, from its seeds you make
oil, as we see, because we’re claiming that that’s the שמן קיק,
Shemen Kik, although obviously not oil that’s good enough to use on
שבת. Shabbat. ובינפוהי נייחין כל בריחי דמערבא, U’vinpohi naychin kol bichei d’Ma’arava,
and under its branches rest all the sick people from the west,
from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So I don’t know what it means
that other sick people don’t, or maybe it means it grows more
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But certainly that evokes a little story
of יונה, Yona, and look, we know that castor oil was used
for health purposes. So it’s interesting though they only mention, so he
says oil and he didn’t say they used the oil for burning
oil, they just said they make oil out of it. So that’s
castor oil, at least if it is a castor plant, which Steinsaltz
says. So maybe that’s the point, castor oil is used for health
purposes, but don’t try to use it for oil purposes, at least
not on שבת. Shabbat. Okay. So that’s what we have for the
קיקיון דיונה, Kikayon d’Yona, another explanation of קיק. Kik. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבה. Amar Rabbah. So now
that’s done with that identification. פתילות שאמרו חכמים אין מדליקין בהן בשבת.
Petilot she’amru Chachamim ein madlikin bahen b’Shabbat.
And here’s answering those, the questions why can’t you use it. So
the reason you can’t use various wicks: מפני שהאור מסכסכת בהן, Mipnei
sheha’ohr mesachsachet bahen,
because those types of wicks the light will flicker. Okay, it could
also say, you know, that the,
that the oil doesn’t get drawn up so well, maybe that’s why
the light flickers. שמנים שאמרו חכמים אין מדליקין בהן, Shemanim she’amru Chachamim
ein madlikin bahen, but the oils that you’re not allowed to use:
מפני שאינן נמשכין אחר הפתילה. Mipnei she’einan nimshachin achar hapetila. That’s because
they do not get drawn well after the wick. If they get
drawn into the wick then they’ll burn, but they don’t necessarily draw
well into the wick. Yes, Charlie, you wanted to add something?
Ricinus is the scientific name for the castor plant.
Oh,
so it’s similar, so basically, so it’s the castor plant is similar
to the castor plant. Well, I don’t know where Steinsaltz got that
identification, he might just have done it out of convenience because that’s
the same thing. But the ערוך Aruch just says Ricinus is some
type of a, is some type of a non-fruit-bearing tree.
And its seeds were used for oil. Okay.
Well, that’s as we know about the castor plant. Okay.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. It says like this:
where were we? Okay.
איבעיא להו מאביי לרבה. Ibaia lehu m’Abaye l’Rabbah.
So אביי Abaye asked from רבה. Rabbah. רבה Rabbah was his
רבי. Rebbe. שמנים שאמרו חכמים אין מדליקין בהם בשבת. Shemanim she’amru Chachamim
ein madlikin bahem b’Shabbat. The
oils that you’re not allowed to use on שבת. Shabbat. מהו שיתן
לתוכן שמן כלשהו Mahu sheyiten l’tochan shemen kolshehu you add a little
let’s say olive oil and then can you use it? Why? Because
he assumes that if you add a little bit of oil, that
mixture, the good oil will cause everything to draw after the wick.
So maybe that should make it acceptable. So what do we say?
מי גזרינן, mi gazrinan,
do we make a גזירה gezera דילמא אתי לאדלוקי בינייהו, deilma ati
leadlukei binhu, that if you allow the mixture you'll come to use
the problematic oils by themselves? או לא, o lo, or do we
not? אמר ליה, amar lei, אין מדליקין. ein madlikin. No, you can’t
use them. You can’t use the mixture. מאי טעמא? mai taama? Why
not? לפי שאין מדליקין, lefi she-ein madlikin, because you can’t use them.
So next time anybody asks me a question, that’s going to be
my answer. Why not? Because you can’t. Don’t ask questions. That’s the
rule. Okay, because I say so. Now that is obviously a very
funny type of an answer. So רש"י Rashi says what does that
mean? It means a type of a לא פלוג. lo plug. You
can’t use the mixtures because you can’t use them by themselves. And
since you can’t use them by themselves, we can’t let you use
the mixtures because one will lead to the other. So that’s how
רש"י Rashi reads it. If you look at the side, some have
a different גרסה girsa which is לפי שאינן נדלקין. lefi she-einan nidlakin.
Not לפי שאין מדליקין lefi she-ein madlikin but לפי שאינן נדלקין, lefi
she-einan nidlakin, that he’s arguing on the fact. He’s saying even those
mixtures do not burn so well. Okay, but that’s not the grammar
we have. The grammar we have is אין מדליקין, ein madlikin, you’re
not allowed to use them. This grammar is אין נדלקין, ein nidlakin,
that mixture does not burn as well as you think it does.
Interestingly the גליון הש"ס Gilyon HaShas of עקיבא איגר, Akiva Eiger, if
you look at the bottom, אין מדליקין לפי שאין מדליקין, ein madlikin
lefi she-ein madlikin, the very bottom of the page, says he gives
other גמרות Gemaras where it sort of says where it basically is
a tautology. Why can’t you do A? Because you can’t do A.
And then interestingly, he quotes at the end of this line, וכן
בלשון התורה, ve-chein bileshon haTorah, ויקרא, Vayikra, אשר יהיה בו מום לא
יקרב, asher yihiyeh bo mum lo yikrav, anybody who has a blemish
cannot bring a sacrifice, כי כל איש אשר בו מום לא יקרב,
ki kol ish asher bo mum lo yikrav, because anybody with a
blemish can’t bring a sacrifice. So basically it’s what we call a
tautology. All right, so anyway he says sometimes you actually find that
which obviously raises a logical problem, how you actually explained it, but
it sort of says that’s the rule. All right. So that’s why
you can’t use a mixture. This whole thing is rabbinic. Yes, but
remember also we’re not even talking about a מצוה mitzvah of lighting
a שבת Shabbos candle. That is not yet been mentioned. We are
just talking about similar to the concerns of reading by light and
of keeping things on the fire. All these concerns around fire is
that you will come to adjust the light. So therefore these types
of oil, which are used even if you’re not going to read
by them, just used for doing regular practices, they don’t want, they
want it to be a clean light so you don’t come to
fiddle with it. Okay, that was obviously a very prevalent concern. But
yes, it’s rabbinic concern. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
איתיבי, Esvei, asked on this. כרך דבר שמדליקין בו על גבי דבר
שאין מדליקין בו, Kerach davar she-madlikin bo al gabei davar she-ein madlikin
bo, if you wrapped a wick that you are allowed to use
on top of something you’re not allowed to use, אין מדליקין בו,
ein madlikin bo, you still can’t use it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אף של בית אבא, af shel
beis abba, or אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, של
בית אבא, shel beis abba, in my father’s house, which is רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, so in the נשיא’s nasi house, היו כורכין פתילה
על גבי אגוז, hayu korechin pesila al gabei egoz, they would wrap
a wick around a nut, ומדליקין, umadlikin, and they would light it.
Now why would you want to wrap a wick around a nut?
Floating wicks, like they do for חנוכה, Chanukah, they have those great
floating wicks, makes lot of sense, it keeps the wick suspended and
that the nut will float and the wick is on the nut.
So he says look, that’s what they used to do. So anyway,
presumably the proof is from the תני מיהא, tani mi-ha, we taught
nevertheless, מדליקין, madlikin, that at least רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says it’s okay if you mix an acceptable wick with
a non-acceptable. Now of course that’s wicks, the other thing is oils.
Anyway, let’s see how the גמרא Gemara responds. And you said you
can’t mix oils together, kosher with a non-kosher. אמר ליה, amar lei,
so he said back, עד דמוספת לי מרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, ad
de-mosaf li mi-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, if you’re challenging me from רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, סייעני ומי דתנא קמא? sei
ani umi de-tanna kamma? How about I have support from the תנא
קמא? Tanna Kamma? De-תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that you are not
allowed to wrap one wick, a kosher wick, around a non-kosher wick.
So גמרא Gemara said, הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that’s not
difficult. I don’t feel the תנא קמא’s Tanna Kamma position is determines.
Why not? מעשה רב, Maaseh rav, which is an important halakhic principle,
which is is that if a thing is not just ruled in
theory but actually acted upon, מעשה רב, Maaseh rav, so here you
have a rabbi actually did it in practice, that carries more halakhic
weight than a theoretical ruling. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel actually said that this is what they used to do
in the house of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So that should be
the more weighty halakhic position and it seems like you can wrap
a kosher wick around a non-kosher one. So similarly, you should be
able to mix kosher oil with non-kosher and use it. So obviously
that’s already quite an analogy. But let’s see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Now let’s see the answer first. מכל מקום קשיא, mi-kol makom
kashya, so now it’s difficult of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, one a wick wrapped around something non-kosher is okay, how
can you say mixing oils is So
I already gave you away the answer. No, there the purpose of
wrapping it was to make it float. But you weren't using the
nut as something that you were using as a wick. You were
just using it as a flotation device. So that's okay. But to
actually mix two things and to use them both as an oil
in a combination or both as a wick in a combination, you
cannot mix a kosher one with a non-kosher one. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי להקפות, ee l'hakpos, if all you're doing is floating
it, מאי טעמא דתנא קמא? mai ta'ama d'Tanna Kamma? Why would the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma disagree? Who should have a problem with making
a floating wick? Who cares if the nut isn't usable by itself?
So the גמרא Gemara says, you're right, it's really not a debate.
כולה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Kulah Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, it's all
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, you could say it's
all, it's all one position. הי וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Hi v'chasuri
mechasra v'hachi katani. Here's how it should be read. כרך דבר שמדליקין
בו על גבי דבר שאין מדליקין בו אין מדליקין בו. Karach davar
she'madlikim bo al gabei davar she'ein madlikim bo, ein madlikim bo. If
you wrap a wick, a kosher wick around a non-kosher wick and
let's just twist them together, let's say, to use them as a
wick, that's no good, because part of it is not kosher. במה
דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, when is this true? להדליק. L'hadlik. If
you're trying to use both as a type of a wick. אבל
להקפות, Aval l'hakpos, if you're trying to float the wick on something
that's not kosher and you're using the non-kosher thing only as a
flotation device, then מותר, muttar, then it's permissible.
שרבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, She'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, של בית
אבא, shel beit abba, היו כורכין פתילה על גבי אגוז, hayu korkhin
ptila al gabei egoz, they would wrap a wick around the nut.
So basically it's saying it is not a debate. The first position
says you cannot wrap, I mean, rather than sort of trying to
change the text, another way of saying what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is that it's not a debate. The first position says you
cannot wrap two whips together... I keep on saying whip... two wicks
together if one of them is not kosher. And רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is just qualifying it and saying, but
that's when they're being used as wicks. To use one as a
flotation device, that's okay, that's what they used to do in my
father's house. Yes.
So my question is, logically speaking,
they say מעשה רב, ma'aseh rav, how do you know that maybe
the first position isn't the consensus opinion, this guy's a דעת יחיד?
da'at yachid? So we say מעשה רב. ma'aseh rav.
Okay, so that always could be
true, that's true, and that's a good question. So the גמרא Gemara
does not- right, very often you have a מעשה, ma'aseh, I mean,
it's a good much larger question about how weighty are the מעשים
ma'asim in the משנה? Mishnah? Because sometimes the משנה Mishnah says, brings
a מעשה ma'aseh and then the question is, is that a חומרה
chumra that he had like we had in the last
פרק? perek? That רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was certainly one of the
people of the נשיאים nesi'im house where he basically got the a
white garment debased to the כהן, kohen, so רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
that was also רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. And
there, we don't rule that way. There it was just a חומרה.
chumra. Okay, but here it was a קולא, kula, so maybe that's
also number one more indicative. If you have a מעשה רב ma'aseh
rav that's a חומרה, chumra, maybe that's your personal חומרה. chumra. If
you have a מעשה רב ma'aseh rav that's more lenient, then that
could be more indicative, well that certainly could be true. Anyway, but
it's a good question how often we actually treat מעשה רב. ma'aseh
rav. But here at least we were willing to accept it for
argument's sake and we still had an answer. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on.
איני, Aini, is this really true? ואמר רב ברונא אמר רב, Ve'amar
Rav Bruna amar Rav, חלב מותך, chelev mehutach, which is liquefied fat.
So if you remember the משנה Mishnah spoke about not using fat
whether it's cooked or not cooked or whatever. נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi
allowed cooked fat, which presumably is the same as חלב מותך, chelev
mehutach, liquefied fat. So according to the חכמים Chachamim you can't use
it.
וקרבי דגים, Ve'kirvei dagim, and the innards of fish. תוספות Tosafot says
this is not fish oil, fish oil is actually okay. So I
don't know what it would be, some other type of thing they
would make from the insides of fish, I mean it can't be
the bones, but whatever it would be, some type of way they
would use that and liquefy it and make oil out of it.
שנימוחו, Shenimochu, that have been liquefied.
אדם נותן לתוכו שמן כל שהוא ומדליק, Adam notan letocho shemen kol
shehu u'madlik, you can mix a little a little olive oil into
it, a little acceptable oil and it's good. So here you see
an explicit ruling against what Rava was saying. Add a little kosher
oil to the non-kosher one and everything becomes okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says let's take a look. So the גמרא, Gemara, very good.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. הני, Hani, those things, those two
things about the fat and the fish, ממשכי בינייהו, mimshachi bnaihu, really
they themselves should be kosher. Really they themselves do draw after the
wick. Right? Remember נחום המדי Nachum Hamadi says you can use a
liquefied fat or cooked fat. So those really should be okay. Why
are they not okay? והני לא ממשכי בינייהו, V'hani lo mimshachi bnaihu,
the rest of the ones in the משנה Mishnah don't draw after
the wick. So why did they say not to use the liquefied
fat? וגזרו רבנן אחלב מותך, V'gazru Rabbanan achelev mehutach, they said don't
use the liquefied fat משום חלב שאינו מותך, mishum chelev she'eino mehutach,
because it'll lead to non-liquefied fat. So the very reason you could
not use the liquefied fat was itself a גזירה, gzira, because it
would get confused with the problematic חלב. chelev. ועל קרבי דגים שנימוחו,
V'al kirvei dagim shenimochu, don't use also liquefied fish innards משום קרבי
דגים שלא נימוחו, mishum kirvei dagim shelo nimochu, it'll lead to cases
where they weren't liquefied. But
in So there the so now
so therefore because those things on their own terms are not problematic,
we were more lenient if you would add a little kosher oil,
you would make it okay. Something that really is not a good
oil, really doesn't draft through the wick, even adding kosher oil won't
help. But something that fundamentally should be okay, and it's just not
okay because of a גזירה, Gezira, there we'll let you do it
if you add some kosher oil. So the גמרא Gemara says why?
וליגזר נמי חלב מותך וקרבי דגים שנימוחו שנתן לתוכם שמן? V'ligzor nami
chelev mutach v'kirvei dagim shenimochu shenatan l'tocham shemen? Why don't we say
even if you've added oil into these like you know liquefied fat
and fish innard, that will lead to משום חלב מותך וקרבי דגים
שנימוחו שלא נתן לתוכם שמן? mishum chelev mutach v'kirvei dagim shenimochu shelo
natan l'tocham shemen? It'll lead to using them without the oil in
them. So the גמרא Gemara asks the obvious answer: האי גופא גזירה,
Hai gufa gezira, the whole thing is a גזירה. gezira. ואנן ניקו
ונגזור גזירה לגזירה? V'anan neiku v'nigzor gezira l'gezira? We're not going to
make a גזירה gezira one protection you know around another protection. Of
course, the גמרא Gemara does very often, but okay it's allowed to
do it when it wants to. But here it says that we
don't do it, at least we're not going to do it here.
So the basic answer is to mix oil with something that is
really not usable oil, it's not good oil, even to mix some
kosher oil won't help. Either because of a גזירה gezira reason, or
because as another way of reading it, because it actually physically doesn't
help. If you're taking oil that really doesn't draft through the wick,
mixing a little kosher oil with it won't help it. But where
it does help is when the oil should have been okay, like
this liquefied fat, but we only said don't use it because it
was could have been confused with a case which was not liquefied,
which would not be good. In that type of a case since
the whole problem with that was not intrinsic, we did say that
we're not going to make a גזירה gezira and if you add
some kosher oil it will be okay. Yes.
So where do we see in this list in the משנה Mishna
about fish
oil though? Because they're saying here don't use this קרבי דגים kirvei
dagim you know so where do we see that that's a problem?
Okay you're right, those that the קרבי דגים kirvei dagim wasn't in
the משנה. Mishna. There are other teachings, not everything is in the
משנה. Mishna. We have other ברייתות braisos to get through so we'll
get so you're saying
that that was basically a ברייתא? braisa?
Well yeah I mean whatever, that's being assumed you're right that's not
in the משנה. Mishna. Now I did want to say something else
about this which is, so on the side there's an interesting question
which we don't have to read, there's a sort of תוספות Tosfos
here a little תוספות Tosfos on the right hand, but anyway he
says, I don't get it. Everything is גזירה לגזירה gezira l'gezira anyway
because the whole reason you can't use these oils is because you
might come to tip the candle and adjust the candle. So to
say don't add oil don't add olive oil to the bad ones,
that's גזירה לגזירה. gezira l'gezira. Don't add olive oil to the bad
ones because you'll come to use the bad ones on their own,
and using the bad ones on their own is only a גזירה
gezira that you might come to tip the candle and adjust the
candle. So you could have said it's all one big גזירה gezira
whatever, but anyway the more interesting is the answer he gives at
the end. If you look here at the side this tiny little
writing on going down the column on the right hand side he
says, וריב"ן פירש, V'Rivan peireish, it's about the line starts with פירש
peireish about six lines from the bottom, דהאי דאמרו לעיל נמשכים אחר
פתילה, d'hai d'amru l'eil nimshachim achar ptila, the issue about being drawn
after the wick, לא משום שמא יטה. lo mishum shema yateh. The
concern is not like I've been telling you all along that you
might come to fiddle and adjust the candle, which would make it
itself a גזירה, gezira, אלא שמא יכבה, ela shema yichbeh,
maybe it'll sputter out and therefore what? וליכא שלום בית. v'leika shalom
bayis. Then you won't have the שלום בית shalom bayis that you
have by having light in the house, but if it's all dark
you're tripping over things you're bumping into people, it's not pleasant experience.
So this is actually important because this is getting to thinking about
the candle lighting as a מצוה. mitzvah. That this whole thing is
not just you happen to be lighting candles and we don't want
you to fiddle with it. Here it's actually saying there's an importance,
you should be lighting candles, we want there to be candles in
the house at night because if it's dark there's not שלום בית
shalom bayis and people have to eat in darkness and they're bumping
into each other and it's not pleasant. So there's actually we're trying
to get you to light candles. And therefore part of the concern
of the oils and the wicks as opposed to what I've been
telling you all along is not just it'll lead to חילול שבת
chilul Shabbos and it'll lead to adjusting, but then it'll undermine the
ability to have light in your house on שבת. Shabbos. You won't
have the candle light if the things go out. So again I
don't know if that's פשט pshat because that has not been at
all introduced into the גמרא, Gemara, but it is worth noting that
as I have said that the idea when does candle lighting become
a מצוה mitzvah as opposed to just a concern that you'll fiddle
with it has yet to be raised in the משנה, Mishna, has
yet to be raised in the גמרא, Gemara, but it does come
up later in the גמרא. Gemara. Some want to argue that it's
early and it was already there in the time of the משנה
Mishna and that's certainly what this position is saying, that part of
the concern of the wicks and the oils is not adjusting and
חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, it's that you won't have the candle light
in your house on שבת. Shabbos.
So this answer works as the only thing you have there, let's
say I have something else that's kosher.
Right well that is true and actually it's worth mentioning about that
that there's another thank you for that because there's another interesting little
תוספות Tosfos because the problem was is that for us it's very
trivial you get paraffin candles, you get whatever, you know it wasn't
always so easy to get if you have this limitation and based
on
what... one of the בעלי התוספות Baalei HaTosfos ששמע באם שיש לו
רק נר אחד כשר בבית, sheshama be'im sheyesh lo rak ner echad
kasher babayit, if you only have one kosher candle, right? and that's
not enough, you need light in a lot of places. על ידי
זה יזכור ולא יטה שאר נרות שבחדר ושבמרתף. Al yedei zeh yizkor
v'lo ya'ateh shear neiros shebachadar v'shebamartef. One kosher candle is enough and
all the other ones don't have to satisfy these criteria. Now that
sounds like a little crazy, right? because who cares if downstairs I
have my kosher candle if I'm trying to do something upstairs by
the candle, I'm going to come to adjust it. But obviously it
was a way of solving a problem that they did not have
enough kosher candles to go around. It also could work in terms
of what Michael was saying, if the issue is not you'll adjust
it, if the issue is that you want to have candlelight in
your house on שבת, Shabbos, maybe one is enough. But that's not
what תוספות Tosfos says. תוספות Tosfos is assuming the problem is that
you'll fiddle with it and he's still trying to deal with a
problem that they did not have enough kosher candles to go around,
so it's interesting to note that. Yes.
So that brings up the question: why shouldn't we have candles in
every single room that we're going to use?
Okay, so we'll get to that when we get to that actual...
we haven't yet been introduced to that in the גמרא Gemara about
the value of candlelight per se. Okay, I should also say the
second answer תוספות Tosfos says maybe if the whole concern is you'll
come to fiddle with it, maybe you can use even the non-kosher
candles to do things that in theory you could do in the
darkness, okay, which is another way of dealing with a reality that
they did not have enough kosher candles to go around. Let's continue
now in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, let's take a look. תני רמי
בר חמא. Tani Rami bar Chama. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar
Chama taught. פתילות ושמנים שאמרו חכמים אין מדליקין בהם בשבת, P'siros ushmanim
she'amru chachamim ein madlikin bahem b'Shabbos,
the things that you can't use on שבת, Shabbos, אין מדליקין בהם
במקדש. ein madlikin bahem b'mikdash. They similarly would not use them in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash for the
מנורה. Menorah. משום שנאמר, Mishum shene'emar, now obviously you have to mention
it by the oils because it says here שמן זית, shemen zayis,
presumably this is more statement about the wicks. משום שנאמר להעלות נר
תמיד, Mishum shene'emar leha'alos ner tamid,
to cause the flame to go up constantly. So what does that
mean? How does that prove anything? הוא תני לה והוא אמר לה,
Hu tani lah v'hu amar lah, he said it and he explained
it. כדי שתהא שלהבת עולה מאליה, K'dei shetehei shalheves olah me'eleha, presumably
this is the way רש"י Rashi explains on the פסוק בהעלותך, pasuk
b'haalosecha,
the הפעיל hiphil form of the verb, to cause the candle to
go up. So you are causing it, but then it is then
going up on its own. It has to be able to be
self-sufficient. And therefore you have to use a type of a wick
that will, that it will burn by, able to be burned by
itself and will not need adjusting. ולא שתהא עולה על ידי דבר
אחר, V'lo shetehei olah al yedei davar acher, not that you need
something else to help it keep on burning. תנן, Tnan, now is
that true? We taught in the משנה. Mishnah. מבלאי מכנסי כהנים ומהמיניהם,
Mibla'ei machnesei kohanim umehameyaniehem, from the worn-out undergarments of the כהנים
kohanim and their belts of the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah, היו מפקיעין,
hayu mafki'in,
they would tear them into strips, ומהם מדליקין שמחת בית השואבה, umeihem
madlikin simchas beis hasho'evah, and they would use it for the torches
and the lights of the מנורה, menorah, I mean these are more
not מנורה menorah in the in the you know in the היכל
heichal but the just מנורות menorot candelabra that they had for the
שמחת בית השואבה. simchas beis hasho'evah. So the גמרא... Gemara... ah, so
you see that and that was not made out of all kosher
wicks because some of that was made out of wool or had
a wool component to it. So how was that acceptable?
So the גמרא Gemara says... no... ומהם מדליקין... umeihem madlikin... oh
I'm sorry, I put the comma in the wrong place. שמחת בית
השואבה שאני. Simchas beis hasho'evah shani. No, that's the שמחת בית השואבה,
simchas beis hasho'evah, that's not the מצוה mitzvah of the מנורה, menorah,
that's just שמחת בית השואבה. simchas beis hasho'evah. So the גמרא Gemara
says תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. דתני רבה בר מתנא.
De-tani Rabba bar Matna. בגדי כהונה שבלו, Bigdei kehunah shebalu, worn out
clothes of the כהנים, kohanim, מפקיעין אותם, mafki'in osam, they would tear
them into strips, ומהם היו עושים פתילה למקדש, umeihem hayu osin p'silah
l'mikdash, they would use it for wicks for the מקדש, mikdash, which
means the מנורה menorah in the מקדש. mikdash.
So that's a problem because some of those had a mixture of
wool and linen and wool is not kosher. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי לאו דכלאים, mai lav de-kilayim, are we not talking that
includes the belts? And the belts had a mixture of wool and
linen, and wool is not a kosher type of a material to
use? גמרא Gemara says לא דבוץ. Lo de-butz. It was the garments
that were not the belt that were made out of all linen,
and those that were made out of all linen, linen is a
kosher wick to use and therefore it was acceptable. Presumably בגדי לבן
bigdei lavan or something? Yeah.
Well, what, yeah, basically. Yes, Rivkah? רש"י Rashi on שמחת בית השואבה
simchas beis hasho'evah says דלאו דאורייתא היא, d'lo d'oraisa hi,
so he's implying that
נר שבת ner shabbos is דאורייתא? d'oraisa? No, he's just explaining that
it's not based on the פסוק... pasuk... no, it's in contrast to
the מנורה, menorah, להעלות נר תמיד. leha'alos ner tamid. We're not dealing
in contrast to this... this is שמחת בית השואבה simchas beis hasho'evah
contrasted to מנורה, menorah, not contrasted to נר שבת. ner shabbos. Okay,
now we turn into a radical shift, not radical, but it'll soon
become an interesting shift. Let's take a look. אמר רב הונא: Amar
Rav Huna: פתילות ושמנים שאמרו חכמים אין מדליקין בהם
בשבת, p'siros ushmanim she'amru chachamim ein madlikin bahem b'shabbos, the wicks and
oils you cannot use on שבת, shabbos, אין מדליקין בהם בחנוכה. ein
madlikin bahem b'chanukah. You can't use on חנוכה, Chanukah, and this is
the... we are now entering into the mother lode for pretty much
the only place that the גמרא Gemara discusses the הלכה. halacha. of
חנוכה. Chanuka. All the laws of חנוכה Chanuka get discussed as a
digression from this discussion about what oils and wicks you can use
on שבת. Shabbos. And the way we enter into it is by
discussing can you use the same oils and wicks, does it have
the same restrictions for חנוכה? Chanuka? Okay, and now we're going to
get into a big discussion about חנוכה. Chanuka. So he says the
ones that you cannot use for שבת Shabbos you also cannot use
for חנוכה, Chanuka, בין בשבת בין בחול, bein beshabbos bein bechol, whether
חנוכה Chanuka falls out on שבת, Shabbos, whether the שבת Shabbos that
falls on חנוכה, Chanuka, whether the, whether the חנוכה Chanuka on שבת,
Shabbos, whether the חנוכה Chanuka on the weekday. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מאי טעמא דרב הונא? mai taama deRav Huna? What's the reason? Because
what's the reason on שבת? Shabbos? Presumably the reason on שבת, Shabbos,
bracketing the other reason we said before, the פשט pshat reason on
שבת Shabbos as the גמרא Gemara is going to indicate right now
is a concern that you will come, well okay anyway, the פשט
pshat reason is you'll come to fiddle with it. But by חנוכה
Chanuka on a weekday, who cares if you fiddle with it? So
what should be the problem of using these candles, these oils and
wicks on חנוכה? Chanuka? קסבר כבתה זקוק לה. kasavar kavsa zekkuk la.
Ah, here's the problem. If they're not so great oils and wicks,
they might sputter out. Now, and what happens by חנוכה Chanuka if
you light it and it sputters out? So there's a debate. Some
say you have to relight it and others say no, as long
as you lit it even if it doesn't burn the whole time
it's okay. That's expressed as כבתה, kavsa, if it burns out, זקוק
לה, zekkuk la, are you obligated to it or not obligated to
it? So if you hold that you have to ensure that it
burns the entire time, then we don't want you to use oils
and wicks that might sputter out because it'll sputter out, you won't
be around, it won't burn and you won't have יצא yotzei the
מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore you have to use very reliable oils and
wicks if you have to ensure that it burns the entire time.
So therefore since he holds כבתה, kavsa, if it goes out, זקוק
לה, zekkuk la, you're responsible for it, we don't want you using
this because it might burn out and you won't pay attention and
you will not have done the מצוה. mitzvah. Now how about on
שבת? Shabbos? So on שבת Shabbos it really is the same problem,
it'll go out and you won't be able to fix it, but
because he singled out שבת Shabbos it sounds like there's a special
שבת Shabbos problem as well. So what's the special שבת Shabbos problem?
Because he also holds מותר להשתמש לאורה mutar lehishtamesh leorah that you
can't use חנוכה Chanuka light, like we say ואין לנו רשות להשתמש
בהן. ve'ein lanu reshus lehishtamesh bahen. Okay, well anyway that's a debate.
Okay, so he says you're actually allowed to do things by the
חנוכה Chanuka light, I mean, so therefore on שבת Shabbos you can't
read, you can't read by any light on שבת, Shabbos, but on
שבת Shabbos I don't know you could eat by the חנוכה Chanuka
light, you could do other things by the חנוכה Chanuka light. Now
if you can do things by the חנוכה Chanuka light you might
come to twiddle with it, right, you might come to adjust it
on שבת. Shabbos. So therefore you don't want to use problematic wicks.
During the weekday because it'll go out and you won't have done
the מצוה, mitzvah, and on שבת Shabbos there's another reason because we
would have allowed you to use it and now if it's not
a problematic, if it's a problematic oil and wick you'll adjust it
and it'll lead to חילול
שבת.
chilul Shabbos.
Alright we're not up to that. רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda amar,
מדליקין בהן בחול אבל לא בשבת. madlikin bahen bechol aval lo beshabbos.
You can do it on the weekday but not on שבת. Shabbos.
Why? So קסבר כבתה אין זקוק לה. kasavar kavsa ein zekkuk la.
If it burns out you are not responsible for it. So therefore
in the weekday totally fine if it burns out not your responsibility.
Now it should be noted that even if you say כבתה אין
זקוק לה, kavsa ein zekkuk la, you have to light it in
a way which it has the potential of burning the entire time.
A, it has to have sufficient oil in it to burn the
entire time. If you light it and it's a windy night out
and as soon as you step away it's going to, it's going
to blow out, you haven't יצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah. So the
assumption has to be that you're using these oils and wicks because
most of the time it'll be fine. I mean let's face it,
if the oils and wicks would always burn out nobody would ever
try to use these in the first place, right, it would be
if they were that unreliable. The point is they're a little unreliable.
So if you're, so even if you say you don't you're not
responsible if it burns out, that's if you lit it and it
was, it had the, you know, reasonable possibility of lasting the entire
time. So we're assuming that's the case but and if in the
chance that it does burn out, fine, it's not your problem. So
therefore you can use these oils and these wicks since you don't
have to ensure it burns the entire time, you just have to
have the potential of doing that. That's why you can use them
during the weekday. Why can you not use them on שבת? Shabbos?
ומותר להשתמש לאורה, umutar lehishtamesh leorah, because you're allowed to use the
light and therefore if you use the light on שבת Shabbos you
will come to adjust it. So you can use it during the
weekday because even if it goes out it's not a problem since
it had the potential. You can't use it on שבת Shabbos because
you'll read, you'll, you'll do things by it and you'll come to
adjust it. אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira as you might be
able to figure therefore four possibilities here, right, what you can do
on the weekday, what you can do on שבת, Shabbos, right, make
a chart for it two by two. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב
מתנה, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav Masna, ואמרי לה ve'amsrei leh אמר
רבי זירא אמר רב, amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav, פתילות ושמנים שאמרו
חכמים אין מדליקין בהם בשבת, psilos ushmanim she'omru chachamim ein madlikin bahem
beshabbos, the things you can't use on שבת, Shabbos, מדליקין בהן בחנוכה,
madlikin bahen bechanuka,
you can use them on חנוכה, Chanuka, בין בחול בין
בשבת. bein bechol bein beshabbos. אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar Rabbi Yirmiya, מאי
טעמא דרב? mai taama deRav?
You could figure this out yourself. What's the reason? So why can
you do it on the weekday, can you use these not great
oils and wicks? Because
if it goes out,
כבתה אין זקוק לה. kavsa ein zekkuk la. קסבר כבתה אין זקוק
לה, kasavar kavsa ein zekkuk la, so therefore even if it goes
out We actually rule this last opinion. On the one hand, this
last opinion is
for אין לנו רשות להשתמש בהם ein lanu reshus l'hishtamesh bahem like
I said, אסור להשתמש לאורה, asur l'hishtamesh l'orah, okay, which makes it
easier to use on שבת, Shabbos, you know, because of the general
חומרא chumra of not using it, not using the light. But for,
that's number one, not using the light to, you know, for doing
other things by the light. And in terms of the שבת Shabbos
issue, in terms of כבתה אין זקוק לה, kavsa ein zakuk lah,
we rule that way and that's very important. Because actually that does
happen, you light your חנוכה Chanukkah candles and sometimes they burn out,
someone especially with oil and various types of things. So we actually
rule that the מצוה mitzvah as long as you've lit it and
has the potential of burning, you don't have to worry if it
does go out. There are some times some interesting questions about that,
like if you're lighting on a windy day, and you know, you
have one of those things that you light outside, you have one
of those things with those glass doors, people, I don't know if
people still do that. When I was in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they had,
have you seen those little houses, whatever, that they have in the
חוץ? chutz? Anyway, so the question is well, if the doors are
open when you're doing the lighting, so the situation at the moment
of lighting is not fit to last the entire time, right? When
you lit, it was not able to last the whole time because
the wind would have blown it out. You've only changed the situation
after the lighting. So does that help? So some say, well, but
you're standing in front of it during the lighting so your body
is blocking it. So that situation, anyway, so there are interesting questions
of exactly how do you determine did it have the potential to
last the entire time, but that is basically the rule. As long
as it had that potential, it does not have to last. And
we will see more of that as we continue. Why can you
not use the light? So, you know, we will see different reasons,
but I will say רש״י Rashi says right now that it's just
because if you use it to benefit from the light, it undermines
its role as פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. People think you lit it
just to, remember, they didn't have electric lights, so people will think
you lit it just to serve as candlelight, if they see you
doing something by it, reading by it, eating by it, or whatever.
So only by not using it for other purposes does it emphasize
that it is there to signify the miracle. That's how רש״י Rashi
understands it, yes.
They raise the question of people might confuse and forget that they're
using the prohibited oil on the שבת Shabbos because
of גזירה.
gezeirah. חנוכה Chanukkah שבת, Shabbos, interestingly, that does not come up. That's
interesting. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So אמרו רבנן קמיה
דאביי משמיה דרבי ירמיה. amru rabanan kamei de-Abaye mishmei de-Rabbi Yirmiyah.
So the rabbis said this to, meaning the rabbinical students said this
to אביי Abaye in the name of רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah, this
thing that the reason of רב Rav is this combination of כבתה
אין זקוק לה kavsa ein zakuk lah and אסור להשתמש לאורה, asur
l'hishtamesh l'orah, which seems pretty straightforward. Anyway, ולא קיבלה, ve-lo kibla, he
didn't accept it. He didn't accept that that was the reason behind
it. Maybe he thought there was some other reason behind it, not
exactly clear what, I mean it seems very straightforward from what we've
been discussing. כי אתא רבין, ki ata Ravin, when רבין Ravin came
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, then he had a different tradition. אמרו
רבנן קמיה דאביי amru rabanan kamei de-Abaye then, they said it to
אביי Abaye משמיה דרבי יוחנן, mishmei de-Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So then they had a different tradition,
but it was basically the same explanation that you can use these
problematic things on חנוכה, Chanukkah, שבת, Shabbos, and חול chol because of
כבתה אין זקוק לה kavsa ein zakuk lah and אסור להשתמש לאורה.
asur l'hishtamesh l'orah. So they said that thing with the explanation. וקיבלה
ve-kibla and he accepted it. Ah, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it,
now I accept. So אמר, amar, then אביי Abaye said אי זכאי,
ei zakai, had I merited, גמרתי שמעתתא מעיקרא. gemarti shema'ata me-ikara. I
would have believed it the first time I heard it. I would
have learned it the first time, I wouldn't have resisted it and
waited until I heard it in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says והא גמרה, ve-ha gemra, what do
you care? Meaning what, oh, had I merited, I would have figured,
I would have accepted it originally. You learned it now, what difference
does it make? So maybe he thought, maybe I would have acted
differently in the intervening years. So the גמרא Gemara gives an interesting
answer. נפקא מינה לגירסא דינקותא. nafka mina le-girsa de-yankusa.
No, the difference is something you learn when you're young. The גמרא
Gemara says when you learn when you're young, something really sticks with
you, it stays with you. So had I merited, I would have
really learned, you know, I would have heard it earlier now. How
young was אביי Abaye when he heard it the first time? He
had rabbinical students teaching him something, presumably it's not like he was
six years old, but nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara says when you learn
it earlier in your life, it sticks with you more. So I
should have just done that earlier. Right, I should have, exactly, I
shouldn't have resisted. It's true, you know, I still remember the גמרא
Gemara I learned when I was like in seventh grade. Anyway, okay,
so that's what we rule now. So at least that's the last
opinion. So now the גמרא Gemara says as follows. וכבתה אין זקוק
לה? ve-kavsa ein zakuk lah? Is it really true that if it
burns out you don't have to relight it, which is now the
opinion we're going by? ורמינהו, u-raminhu, I'll ask you on this: מצותה
משתשקע החמה עד שתכלה רגל מן השוק. mitzvasah mi-she-tishka ha-chama ad she-tichla
regel min ha-shuk.
The מצוה mitzvah of חנוכה Chanukkah is from the time the sun
goes down, I'll discuss that in a minute. until people stop, until
the foot, the, has stopped from the marketplace, meaning until people are
no longer milling about in the streets. So the גמרא Gemara understands
that means that it has to burn the entire time. That's certainly
one way of reading it. The מצוה mitzvah is that it burns
from the time the sun goes down till people stop milling about
in the street. מאי לאו, Mai lav, does that not mean דאיכבתה
הדר מדליק לה, de'ichavah hadar madlik lah, that if it burns out
you have to re-light it? The מצוה mitzvah extends the entire period
of time and it has to burn the entire period of time.
גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, that's not what it means. דאי לא
אדליק מדליק. de'ee lo adlik madlik. It means that this is the
time when you can do the הדלקה. hadlakah. You have this entire
range of time to do the מצוה. mitzvah. It's not that it
has to burn the entire time. It's from the sunset till people
stop walking around is when the מצוה mitzvah can be done, anytime
within this range. You see that as opposed to saying it has
to burn the entire time.
ואינמי לשיעורה, Ve'inama l'shiurah, or it means that it has to have,
and this word I was saying, the potential of burning that long.
So it has to have the oil that it could burn the
entire time, but it doesn't mean that if it goes out you
have to re-light it. And that's exactly how we rule, that it
has to have the potential to burn that time. I'll read one
more thing and then I'll discuss what that means להלכה. l'halachah. עד
שתכלה רגל מן השוק, Ad shetichleh regel min hashuk, and עד כמה,
ad kama, how much, meaning how long? What does it mean who
stops walking around in the marketplace? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן עד דכליא ריגלא דתרמודאי, amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan ad d'kalia regla de'tarmudai, until
the legs of the תרמודאים Tarmudayim are no longer in the marketplace.
Who are the תרמודאים? Tarmudayim? So רש"י Rashi says that those were
wood sellers and that they would be and that they would
be the last people to go home because everybody else would go
home, it would be nightfall, they'd start lighting their fires and they'd
realize, you know, that they needed more wood. So the wood sellers
had to be open the latest so people could go and get
the wood from them even after it got dark. רש"י Rashi also
says, well why aren't, you know, רש"י Rashi says they were non-Jews.
Presumably he's saying that because, like, well, when did they light חנוכה
Chanukah candles? So he solves it by saying that they were non-Jews.
Now that raises a couple of interesting questions. First of all, let's
ask when משתשקע החמה mishetishka hachamah is. Normally you'd think that means
sunset,
but a number of ראשונים Rishonim for various reasons, which I'm not
going to go into right now, say that it means, say that
it means not, not really sunset, but it means צאת הכוכבים, tzeit
hakochavim, although it's a funny use of the word משתשקע החמה. mishetishka
hachamah. Partly having to do maybe with the idea that nobody can
see it if it's during sun, if it's only right after sunset.
Of course maybe it's a bigger פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa if you're
doing it right at sunset because why else are you lighting candles
in, you don't need the light yet. Anyway, so there's that debate
number one: does the מצוה mitzvah start by sunset or does it
start at צאת
הכוכבים? tzeit hakochavim? Question number two is when is this תכלה רגל
מן השוק? tichleh regel min hashuk? So the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
rules, you know, following other, whatever, ראשונים Rishonim that says, well, that's
about a half hour later. Now that might have been true in
his time, okay. Nowadays, when do people start going, you know, all
go home, and there's mostly not people on the street, especially if
you say like רש"י, Rashi, you include the non-Jews as well, you
know, my God, who knows, till midnight or something. There's a story
about some rabbi that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that would like
keep his מנורה menorah burning till like midnight. Why? Because he lived
across the street from a movie theater and the last movie got
out at midnight. So he had to keep it burning till midnight.
We generally, there are some people that do that, that really try
to put in a lot of oil. I mean if you use
these oil מנורות menorahs as they do burn a long time, you
know,
anyway, that really do keep it burning for a while. Now again,
it depends where you live. Are you living in Manhattan? Are you,
you know, if you're living in a, in the suburbs or whatever
and you know, and you're learning somewhere that, you know, it is
true that not too many people are milling around. Everybody nobody is
here but fundamentally basically everything, nothing going on, right? Anyway, so that
could make a difference. The other reason, but, but most people do
say with all that being said, they accept the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch and they say it just has to burn for a half
hour. Part of the reason for that is as we're going to
see, because as you understand the reason it's, this is the time
is because people want, you, people should be seeing it, פרסומי ניסא.
pirsumei nisa. But there became a time when they moved it indoors
and not outdoors because there was סכנה. sakanah. There were certain, you
know, the non-Jews weren't allowing it and so on, and then it
became focused as a פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa for the family, not
a פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa for the outsiders. And that allowed us
to have greater leniencies in a sense that even if, you know,
it's not exactly at this time, even if it's later in the
night, because even if there's nobody outside, at least people inside see
it, and also the amount of time that it has to burn
we can be satisfied with a half hour. But that's a whole
history of development. Fundamentally it was for the people outside and it
really had to be visible for the time that most people were
still out and about. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
מצות חנוכה נר איש וביתו. mitzvat Chanukah ner ish u'beito.
Okay, so it, the מצות חנוכה mitzvat Chanukah is one candle for
one person for the household. Not everybody in the house, no, one
person
for the house, right?
Right. One person, one candle, not per person. Right. One candle, one
person lights one candle. in the household, and that's enough. Okay, that's
the fundamental
מצוה. mitzvah. והמהדרין, Vehamadrin, those that are you know more beautifying the
מצות, mitzvos,
נר לכל אחד ואחד, ner l'chol echad v'echad, what each individual lights
a candle. והמהדרין מן המהדרין, Vehamadrin min hamahadrin, right now, that's the
whole thing like, you know, here it's interesting, now we use it
as like super frum, like super glatt kosher, like מהדרין מן המהדרין
הכשר. mehadrin min hamahadrin hechsher. But you know, but here it doesn't
mean הידור, hiddur, here means to beautify the מצוה. mitzvah. It's not
used as חומרות, chumras, it's you like, you know, חומרות chumras in
the sense of stringencies like forbidding things, it's used in the sense
of to do a מצוה mitzvah in the most beautiful way. For
those that are seeking to most beautify the מצוה, mitzvah, how do
you do it? So בית שמאי אומרים יום ראשון מדליק שמונה, Beis
Shammai omrim yom rishon madlik shmoneh, the first day you do eight,
מכאן ואילך פוחת והולך, mikan v'eilech pocheis v'holech, you go down, 8,
7, 6, 5, 4. ובית הלל אומרים, uBeis Hillel omrim, בית הלל
Beis Hillel says יום ראשון מדליק אחת, yom rishon madlik achas, the
first day you light one, מכאן ואילך מוסיף והולך, mikan v'eilech mosif
v'holech, and you add. What's the debate? Now before we get to
what's the debate about I should say there's an interesting מחלוקת ראשונים.
machlokes rishonim. תוספות Tosafos says when you get to the בית הלל
או בית שמאי, Beis Hillel o Beis Shammai, you're going back to
one thing for the whole house. Because if each individual lights, you
know, and then on one night you have five people in the
house and each person is lighting, you know, two candles or something,
nobody knows, they see ten candles, they don't know what to make
of it of all of that. So if you want it to
be symbolized the number of nights, then you only can have one
מנורה, menorah, you know, one חנוכיה, chanukiah, you know, one lighting because
then the number is clear. But if you have multiple people lighting,
then the number is not clear. So that's what תוספות Tosafos says.
The רמב"ם Rambam says no, the individual you know each one builds
on the next so when you get to the מהדרין מן המהדרין,
mehadrin min hamahadrin, every individual is lighting according to the number of
nights. And that's the way you know, interestingly, that's the way the
אשכנזים פוסקים, Ashkenazim pasken, is like the ספרדים, Sefardim, like the רמב"ם.
Rambam. And it's an interesting crossover פסק psak of the בעל הבית.
baal habayis.
Or really does it, not every single person is doing it.
Oh yes, that's also true but I won't get that- that's a
good point. That the רמב"ם Rambam says that even when you do
it represent- about the number of people in the house, Micah is
correct, it's not that each member of the house lights, it's that
the בעל הבית baal habayis lights for the number of people in
the house. So that's also an interesting variation. Okay, anyway let's see
what this debate is about. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, פליגי בה תרי
אמוראי במערבא, peligi bah trei amorai b'maarava, two אמוראים Amoraim in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael debate what this is all about. רבי יוסי בר
אבין ורבי יוסי בר זבידא. Rabbi Yose bar Abin v'Rabbi Yose bar
Zvida. You might remember that they also had interesting debates about like
על קן ציפור יגיעו רחמיך. Al kanchipor yagi'u rachamecha. These two
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yoses from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Yep, these two
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yoses from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. חד אמר טעמא
דבית שמאי כנגד ימים הנכנסים וטעמא דבית הלל כנגד ימים היוצאים. Chad
amar ta'ama d'Beis Shammai k'neged yamim hanichnasin v'ta'ama d'Beis Hillel k'neged yamim
hayotzin. The most obvious explanation, בית שמאי Beis Shammai is counting the
days that are yet to come and בית הלל Beis Hillel is
counting the days that you're currently in, day one, day two, day
three.
וחד אמר טעמא דבית שמאי כנגד פרי החג, V'chad amar ta'ama d'Beis
Shammai k'neged parei hachag, בית שמאי Beis Shammai is like the- the
oxen brought on סוכות Sukkos that the number would go down with
each מוסף, musaf, 13, 12, 11, 10.
וטעמא דבית הלל דמעלין בקודש ואין מורידין, v'ta'ama d'Beis Hillel d'ma'alin b'kodesh
v'ein moridin, that you go up in קדושה kedusha not down, so
you want to increase the number of candles. I'll read a little
bit more and then I'll say something about this. אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan, שני זקנים היו בצידן, shnei zekeinim hayu b'Tziyada, there were two
elders in Sidon. חד עביד כדברי בית שמאי וחד עביד כדברי בית
הלל. Chad avid k'divrei Beis Shammai v'chad avid k'divrei Beis Hillel. One
did like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, one did like בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. Interesting. So there was a time that it was not yet
you know
consensus of בית הלל. Beis Hillel. זה נותן טעם לדבריו כנגד פרי
החג, Ze nosein ta'am l'divrav k'neged parei hachag, that oh, I'm going
like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, like the- like the oxen of the
סוכות מוסף Sukkos musaf which go down in number. וזה נותן טעם
לדבריו דמעלין בקודש ואין מורידין. V'ze nosein ta'am l'divrav d'ma'alin b'kodesh v'ein
moridin. Okay, that you go- that you go up, you do not
go down. So let me say something about what this debate is
about.
The
מהר"ל Maharal has an interesting approach and he says the difference between
8 starting with 8 and starting with 1 is that 8 focuses
on potential and 1 focuses on actual. Like the first day there
are 8 potential days to come, you know, and whereas the one
is we're actually in the first day, you're actually in the second
and that's interesting 'cause some want to say see some of the
debates of בית שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai uBeis Hillel along those
lines of בית שמאי Beis Shammai being more about potential, בית הלל
Beis Hillel actual. I'll just indicate that without fleshing that out. A
nicer explanation I think is you know, well one is sort of
like it's- it's funny, it's like the optimist and the pessimist, right?
Are you counting how many days you have left- oh, only eight
days left, only seven days- if you're counting down it's more like
you're looking towards the end. But if you're counting up, one, two,
three, it's like you don't even know when it's going to end
and I think it's more sort of like an optimistic view as
opposed to you know every day it's getting- getting worse, there are
fewer days left. So you know, so it's like the glass half-empty,
half-full. My wife once said she was once trying to explain when
she was very young to her younger brother the difference between the
optimist and the pessimist. So she said, "Okay, let's say you have
a glass that's
half-empty."
Anyway, so בית שמאי Beis Shammai is looking at it as half-empty,
בית הלל Beis Hillel is looking at it as half-full. Now that
could be true, you know. בית שמאי Beis Shammai tends to have
a more pessimistic view of human nature and of the fact that
we'll come to sin and you know בית הלל Beis Hillel it's
interesting to see maybe some of those differences a little bit along
those lines. The most beautiful explanation though I saw was from רב
זווין, Rav Zevin, רב שלמה זווין, Rav Shlomo Zevin, who says, who
says the following. He says look, he says the מצוה mitzvah of
what happened on חנוכה Chanukah is you had to go to war
against the, you know, the Greeks and the Hellenists and it required,
you know, violence and it required focusing on the evil and eradicating
the evil. But the question is like what's our message for, for,
you know, general religious life? That was needed at the time. Is
our message to focus on, you know, on destroying the evil or
is our message to spread goodness? Like is it, you know, better
to light one candle than to curse the darkness? So he says
that's the difference. בית שמאי Beis Shammai is focused on the רע,
ra, on getting rid of the רע. ra. So he says, you
know, and that's why the idea of like going down because the
פרי החג Parei Hachag represent the nations of the world, so if
you see those as evil, it's about them מתמעטין והולכין mitmatin veholechin
and going down and whatever. And בית הלל Beis Hillel sees it
as about the spreading of the good, מעלין בקודש. maalin bakodesh. And
to some degree he says maybe it's how we look at the
fire, at, at the נר. ner. Do we look at it as
light or do we look at it as fire? You look at
it as fire to destroy the bad or do you look at
it as light to spread the good? So he says that's possibly
the difference between בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
which I thought was a very beautiful explanation. So now let's see
as the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: נר חנוכה מצוה
להניחה על פתח ביתו מבחוץ. Ner Chanukah mitzvah lehannichah al petach beito
mibachutz. So the מצוה mitzvah as we said is to for, for
the people on the outside to see it, so you should put
it in the doorway, in your doorframe on the outside of your
doorframe so people walking by will see it in the doorframe. אם
היה דר בעליה? Im hayah dar be'aliyah? No.
No. This is because right, so this is because people will be
walking in the courtyard. Michael is correct, the house is opened up
into the courtyard. So the fundamental focus is on the people that
are going to be coming and going and walking in the courtyard,
not in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. At least that's the way
רש"י Rashi explains it. אם היה דר בעליה, Im hayah dar be'aliyah,
now if you're on the second story so nobody in the courtyard
would see it, then מניחה בחלון הסמוכה לרשות הרבים. menichah bechalon hasmuchah
lereshus harabbim. Then you have it at the window facing like the
outside of the courtyard towards the, towards the public domain and at
least people in the public domain will see it even though people
in the courtyard won't. ובשעת הסכנה, Ubesha'at hasekanah, if it's a time
of danger
where you know the, the non-Jews either they weren't allowing them to
do it because it was a religious ritual or רש"י Rashi also
refers to if you look at רש"י Rashi he says, סכנה, sekanah,
it's I don't even know where to tell you where it is,
it's about 20 lines from the bottom, שהיה להם לפרסיים חוק ביומי
דם שלא יבערו נר אלא בבית עבודה זרה שלהם. shehayah lahem leFarsiyim
chok beyomei dam shelo yiva'aru ner ella beveit avodah zarah shelahem. He
speaks about other people not lighting candles. This really is consistent with
Zoroastrianism that has the whole idea of a sacred fire. So he
says that maybe it wasn't just they were trying to get rid
of the Jewish practice but more that it was seen as a
violation of their sort of religious practice for other people to be
doing things in some type of a using fire in some sacred
way. So whatever the reason was when it was not acceptable to
be lighting it outdoors, so מניחה על שולחנו ודיו. menichah al shulchano
vedayo. You just keep it on your table and you do it
and that's enough. And that's as I said the מצוה mitzvah transitioning
from פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa to the outside to פרסומי ניסא pirsumei
nisa to the inside and then there's, you know, that's how it's
ruled in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. The question becomes nowadays where
we do have ברוך השם Baruch Hashem religious freedom, how much you
know should that go, be going back and how much should we
be, you know, say it is acceptable to light on the inside,
how much at least should we try to be putting it in
the window where people can see it which I think ברוך השם
Baruch Hashem what most people try to do. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
says רבא, Rava, צריך נר אחר להשתמש לאורה. tzarich ner acher lehistamesh
le'orah. And this is the idea of the שמש. shamash. You need
another candle if, in order to use it. Now it could be
just saying if you want to use the light we said you're
not allowed to, so what we'll do is you'll have a שמש,
shamash, an extra candle, so that you can at least, you know,
get, that light will be acceptable to use. But רש"י Rashi sort
of makes it more about, less about the איסור issur of using
the light and more about what it was about. For רש"י Rashi
the איסור issur of using the light was so that it's obvious
it's פרסום הנס. pirsum haneis. People don't think that you are coming
to do it for the light. So therefore what רש"י Rashi says
is, here in order to emphasize the פרסום הנס, pirsum haneis, light
a separate candle so the separate candle will be clear that you
could have used that for your candlelight, so why are you lighting
this? This must be for some other reason, this must be for
the פרסום הנס. pirsum haneis. ואי איכא מדורה, Ve'i ika medura, now
if there's a flame, if there's like a, you know, like a
bonfire going, לא צריך, lo tzarich, then you don't need a separate
candle. Obviously you already have light in the house, so this creates
the פרסום הנס pirsum haneis by itself. ואי אדם חשוב הוא, Ve'i
adam chashuv hu, if you're a חשוב chashuv person who would not
you know use the fire of a, of a torch presumably that
would somehow I don't know it would be more appropriate, more, you
know, to use candlelight than a big torch light, then אף על
גב דאיכא מדורה, af al gav de'ika medura, even if there is
this torch, צריך נר אחר, tzarich ner acher, you need a candlelight
so again people will say that you're using the candlelight to provide
you the light, what's the purpose of the, of these other things,
must be not for light, must be for פרסום הנס. pirsum haneis.
So nowadays obviously that we have electric lights, you really don't need
a שמש. shamash. Okay, so this idea of the שמש shamash is
to make it clear that the other stuff which is why we
can't use the other stuff for the light but also to make
it clear to everybody that we don't. need to use it for
the light as we have another light going. Now we will see
another issue about the שמש shamash about can you how do you
light from one candle to the next. But this is the issue
about the שמש shamash so that it's clear that this I don't
need this for the light, which for nowadays, having having electrical lights
obviously is the case of the מדורה. madurah. Let's take a look
now as it switches from הלכה halacha to a little historical discussion.
Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Wait a minute.
מאי חנוכה? Mai Chanukah? What is the Chanukah? What's Chanukah? דתנו רבנן,
Detanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: בכ"ה בכסלו, Bekaf-hey beKislev,
on the 25th of Kislev, יומי דחנוכה תמניא אינון, yomei deChanukah temanya
inun, these eight days of Chanukah, דלא למספד בהון, dela lemispad behon,
that you can't have a hesped, ודלא להתענות בהון, udela lehitanot behon,
and you cannot do a תענית. taanit. Now this is a quote
from מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit. We mentioned מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit before,
a very early work, a fast- some very early written work that
listed the days that you can't have a תענית taanit and that
you don't do a hesped and in this was written one of
the days was the 25th of Kislev which was Chanukah. Now in
מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit, Chanukah does not get bigger play than anything
else. Like there's a lot of days that you can't fast for
a lot of historical events, 99 percent of which we've totally forgotten,
but one of the things in that list was 25th of Kislev
Chanukah and that we end there. Now there is a gloss written
on- מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit was from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. There's
a gloss written on מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit that now the גמרא
Gemara quotes that was written in בבל Bavel that expands and amplifies
what was the basic sort of lines of מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit.
And now it- this is incorporating that gloss and that is telling
us what actually happened on Chanukah. So let's take...
Yes, we have מגילת
תענית
Megillat
Taanit with the gloss on it. I'll bring in an edition of
it tomorrow. I forgot today. Okay, but they have a nice academic
edition and the whole thing. Okay, and this גמרא Gemara is- so
the first line is from the original מגילה, Megillah, which is from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and now the continuation is from the gloss.
Okay. כשנכנסו יוונים להיכל, Keshenichnasu Yevanim leHeichal, when the when the Greeks
entered into the היכל, Heichal, טימאו כל השמנים שבהיכל, timu kol hashemanim
shebaHeichal,
they impurified all of the oils in the היכל, Heichal,
which is, you know, the קודש kodesh part of the holy part
of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, which is where the מנורה menorah
is. וכשגברה מלכות בית חשמונאי ונצחום, Ucheshegavrah malchut Beit Chashmonai venitzchum,
and when the חשמונאי Chashmonai were victorious, ובדקו ולא מצאו אלא פך
אחד של שמן, uvadku velo matzu ela pach echad shel shemen, they
only found one, a little פך, pach, how do they point out-
a
little vessel, jug, whatever, yeah. Anyways, a cruse, flask of oil שהיה
מונח בחותמו של כהן גדול. shehayah munach bechotamo shel Kohen Gadol.
It was sealed with the seal of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
which wasn't broken, so that nobody had touched the oil. And so
that could not have become טמא, tamei, assuming that there was not
a concern of טומאת מת tumat meit I guess, or maybe it
was a כלי חרס kli cheres so if it was sealed nothing
was מטמא metamei what was inside of it. ולא היה בו אלא
להדליק יום אחד, Velo hayah bo ela lehadlik yom echad, and only
had enough for one day. נעשה בו נס, Naasah bo nes, a
miracle occurred, והדליקו ממנו שמונה ימים, vehidliku mimenu shemonah yamim, and it
lasted for eight days. לשנה אחרת קבעום ועשאום ימים טובים, Leshannah acheret
kevaum vaasaum yamim tovim, the next year
they made it a יום טוב, Yom Tov, בהלל והודאה, beHallel vehodaah,
with הלל Hallel and thanks. So רש"י, Rashi, it's thanks is like
saying, so if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he makes
an important point. בהלל והודאה, beHallel vehodaah, לא שאסורים במלאכה. lo sheasurim
bemelachah. It's not a יום טוב, Yom Tov, it's not אסור במלאכה,
assur bemelachah, אלא לקרות הלל ולומר... ela likrot Hallel velomar... what's the
הודאה? hodaah? על הנסים Al Hanissim בהודאה. behodaah. So it has the
saying of הלל, Hallel, the saying of על הנסים, Al Hanissim, and
that's what they established. Interestingly, it doesn't say- what does it not
say they did? They did not say what's the other part of
the יום טוב Yom Tov other than saying הלל Hallel and על
הנסים? Al Hanissim? Not light- what? Lighting the candles. Lighting the candles!
It doesn't say that they said to light the candles. Okay, by
the way, as opposed to as opposed to
פורים Purim
where there's a מצוה mitzvah of סעודה, seudah, משלוח מנות. mishloach manot.
Here by חנוכה, Chanukah, it's not a יום טוב, Yom Tov, but
it's for lighting of the candles, it's הלל Hallel and it's על
הנסים. Al Hanissim. Now I want to say something about this which
is a couple things. First of all, just very briefly, there's you
know, there's been hundreds of books written on figuring out this on
on analyzing this because the first question that gets asked is, so
it was really only a seven-day miracle because there was enough oil
to last one day. So the answer- I never understood this question
as a kid, I finally found the מהר"ל Maharal said it, but
to me the answer was obvious, it's that every day only one-eighth
of the oil burned. So there was a miracle each day that
one-eighth of the oil was able to burn for the entire day.
But you'd be surprised at the wide range of other answers that
are given to that. Actually, one important answer which will get to
a point I'm about to make that the בית יוסף Beit Yosef
says is, no, the first day was to commemorate the war, the
victory of the war. The rest was the victory of the oil.
Anyway, so that's one question. The other question is, who cares that
it was טמא? tamei? Whatever happened to טומאה הותרה בציבור? tumah hutrah
betzibur? Or, why didn't they just make new oil? You know, and
there's a whole series of answers around that which we cannot fully
explore. But what I do want to say though, and I was
going to read it inside but we don't have time but I
will allow you to read it, is a beautiful explanation of the
מהר"ל Maharal who asks this question about... Whatever happened to the war,
why is that not mentioned? And what he also points out before
he gives the answer is that if you look in the על
הניסים, Al Hanissim, right, the על הניסים Al Hanissim does not mention
the miracle of the oil. The על הניסים Al Hanissim just mentions
the war. Now actually historically, all of the sources that were contemporaneous
and all of the sources from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael do not
mention the miracle of the oil. So whether you've got, you know,
Josephus, whether you've got the book of the of the of you
know of the Maccabees, whether you have the על הניסים, Al Hanissim,
they all mention the war, they mention what does חנוכה Chanukah mean?
The rededication of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, right, the dedication of
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash was what?
And also the
rest, well yeah, but that's a דרש. drash. It really means the
חנוכת המזבח, Chanukat HaMizbeach, right, the rededication of the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, okay, and the eight days it says in the book of
Maccabees had to do with some parallel to סוכות Sukkot and so
on,
and it all mentions the victory of the war and the rededication
of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, does not mention this at all.
When actually Josephus is explaining why we light candles on חנוכה, Chanukah,
he says, well, maybe because light symbolizes redemption or whatever, makes no
mention of any miracle with the oil. The only mention of the
miracle of the oil is in this Babylonian source of the gloss
on the on the on the
what do you call it on the on the מגילת תענית. Megillat
Taanit.
So this is an issue about why is we emphasizing here the
miracle of the oil if everything else emphasizes the miracle of the
war. And what the מהר״ל Maharal says is he says because the
miracle of the oil showed the significance of the war. The war
you could have said this was us, it wasn't God. So what
the miracle of the oil was about was that you was to
give this little miraculous thing in order to appreciate how the miracle
of the war was all about God's helping us and was all
about and therefore it's connected also to the rededication of the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, meaning it all gave us the sort of the
religious significance to what it was about. So he tries to read
in the miracle of the oil as a way of demonstrating what
that significance was of the of the war and of the rededication
of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, and I will end by saying
that some also try to sort of connect it, why of all
מצוות mitzvot here do we have an idea of מהדרין, mehadrin, מהדרין
מן המהדרין, mehadrin min hamehadrin, right? We don't have this elsewhere. And
so one type of answer is sort of a similar idea. Number
one, God went out of his way, there's two ways of saying
it. With following the מהר״ל, Maharal, God went out of his way
to show his sort of love to us by demonstrating in this
obvious way of this miracle that the war and everything was coming
from God. So we go out of the way as well to
be do the פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa.
And that you know so there sort of giving a certain parallel
but trying to bring this miracle of the oil into the more
sort of I would say weighty historical events. And I think it's
an important educational question, how much when we give the message of
what חנוכה Chanukah is about, is it all about the miracle of
the oil or is it all about the importance about the war
of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim and the independence and the freedom of practice
and religion and all of those various other issues? So, you know,
that's a restoring of some of that balance. So for anybody who
wants to, you can take a look at that.